<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A memorial from His Most Christian Majesty presented by the Count de Briord, his Ambassador Extraordinary to the States General of the United Provinces at the Hague, December 4, 1700 containing his reasons for accepting the late King of Spain's will in favour of the Duke of Anjou.</title>
            <author>France. Sovereign (1643-1715 : Louis XIV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B26241</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15701716_38595</idno>
  <idno type="VID">38595</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248512118</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3128A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36485</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">15701716</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B26241)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38595)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1152:54 or 1835:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A memorial from His Most Christian Majesty presented by the Count de Briord, his Ambassador Extraordinary to the States General of the United Provinces at the Hague, December 4, 1700 containing his reasons for accepting the late King of Spain's will in favour of the Duke of Anjou.</title>
                  <author>France. Sovereign (1643-1715 : Louis XIV)</author>
                  <author>Louis XIV, King of France, 1638-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by J. Nutt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Price 4d."</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Bodleian Library (reel 1152) and Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (reel 1835).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  II, --  King of Spain, 1661-1700 --  Will.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">United Provinces of the Netherlands. --  Staten Generaal.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Spanish Succession, War of, 1701-1714.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">France --  Foreign relations --  1643-1715.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Spain --  Kings and rulers --  Succession.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-02 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38595:1"/>
            <p>A MEMORIAL From His Most Christian Majesty, Presented by The Count <hi>de Briord,</hi> His Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sador Extraordinary to the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> at the <hi>Hague, December</hi> 4. 1700.</p>
            <p>Containing His REASONS FOR Accepting the late King of <hi>SPAIN</hi>'s WILL, in Favour of the Duke of <hi>ANJOU.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and sold by <hi>J. Nutt,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall,</hi> 1700. Price 4 d.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:38595:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:38595:2"/>
            <head>A Memorial from His Most Christian Majesty, presented by the Count <hi>de Briord,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IF the States General seem at present to be surprized, at the King's accepting the Will of the late King of <hi>Spain,</hi> they will in a little time thank his Majesty for preferring on this Occasion the Peace of the Publick, to the Advantage of his own Crown. If they take time to examine, with their usual Prudence, the infinite Troubles which the Treaty of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition would produce, that same Prudence will oblige them to desist from the Demand, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Memorial which they have put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Hands of his Majesty's Ambassador. They will confess, that the Misfortunes of obtaining it, will be common to all <hi>Europe;</hi> and certainly they will be of Opinion, that there's nothing can be a greater Contradiction, than to abandon the Design of the Treaty, for the sake of adher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Terms of it.</p>
            <p>For we must of Necessity at this Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture distinguish betwixt the one and the other.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38595:3"/> The Design and the <hi>Terms</hi> were united whilst the K. of <hi>Spain</hi> lived, but the last <hi>Will</hi> of that <hi>Prince</hi> &amp; his Death, make such a Difference betwixt 'em, that the <hi>Design</hi> is absolutely <hi>destroy'd</hi> if the <hi>Terms</hi> stand. The former maintains a General Peace, the latter causes an Universal War. This Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation alone makes a true Decision, as to what Choice we are to make, in order to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our selves to the principal Object of the Treaty, as explain'd by the first Articles of it, <hi>viz. To maintain the General Peace of</hi> Europe, <hi>to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the Publick Repose, and to avoid a new War, by an Accommodation of those Disputes and Differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences that may happen upon the Subject of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish Succession, or by the Ʋmbrage of too many Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions being united under one and the same Prince.</hi> 'Twas upon such Motives that the King took with his Allies, the necessary Measures for preventing a War, which the Spanish Succession seemed unavoidably to threaten.</p>
            <p>It was not his Majesty's Design to acquire by a Treaty the Kingdoms of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> the Province of <hi>Guipuscoa</hi> and the Dutchy of <hi>Lorain;</hi> his Allies had no Right to those Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and perhaps he might have obtain'd more considerable Advantages by his Arms, if he had design'd to make use of them on the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s death. But his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:38595:3"/> principal End being to maintain the Peace, he treated upon that Foundation alone. He suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the Dauphin to content himself with the Share allotted him, in lieu of all his Right to the whole Succession of the Kingdoms of <hi>Spain.</hi> But it happens that the Measures then taken, with a design to preserve the Publick Peace, produce a quite contrary Effect, and that they engage <hi>Europe</hi> in a new War: If it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come necessary for preserving the Peace, to use Means different from those that were proposed for that End. If this new Way occasion no Prejudice to the Potentates in Alliance with his Majesty, all the Disadvantage falls upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; and if he is willing to Sacrifice his own Interests to the General Good of Christendom, it not only depends upon his Majesty, to do it, but he has likewise ground to believe, that his Allies will commend his Moderation, and his Love to Peace, rather than complain of a Change, which the Publick Welfare requires, and that they will thank him for a Resolution, which 'twas impossible for him to defer, without expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing himself at the same time to long and bloody Wars, which his Majesty, in Concert with them, was willing to prevent.</p>
            <p>The first Appearances of it were already plain enough. The Spaniards, being zealous to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38595:4"/> their Monarchy entire, made Preparations on all sides for a Defence. The <hi>Milanese,</hi> the Kingdoms of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily,</hi> the Provinces, the Places comprehended in the Partition, all of them put themselves in a Condition, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Union with the Body of the Spanish Monarchy. The Nation demanded only a King whom they might lawfully own: And tho' the Inclinations of all the Dominions of the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> did universally carry them to desire a Prince of <hi>France,</hi> the Subjects of that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy would have been Loyal to any other <hi>Prince</hi> appointed by the Will of the late Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King, exclusive of the Dauphin's Sons.</p>
            <p>They were left at no uncertainty, but as to the Acceptation, for the late King having at last done Justice to the true Heirs, their Refusal would have authorised <hi>Spain</hi> to submit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the Archduke. No Body in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood will doubt but the Emperor would have accepted the Will. The Succession of <hi>Spain</hi> for his second Son, was the main Design of his long Negotiations at <hi>Madrid.</hi> His Treaties in the Empire were for that same End. He did not refuse to sign the Partition but in hopes of that. 'Twill be hard to perswade any Man to believe, that when he was just ready to reap the Fruits of so much, Labour, he would be willing to lose
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38595:4"/> them, and rest contented with the same Offers, that he had constantly rejected.</p>
            <p>Thus the Archduke becoming K. of <hi>Spain</hi> by the Consent of the whole Nation, there must be a Necessity, in order to execute the Treaty, to Conquer the Kingdoms and Dominions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd for the Share of the Dauphin. There would be no room left to alledge the Injury done to the lawful Heirs, for the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had own'd their Right. There must be a Necessity of attacking a Prince declared Successor of all the Dominions depending on the Monarchy.</p>
            <p>His new Subjects being accustomed to Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty toward their Sovereigns, being informed of the Refusal of the true Heirs, would be as Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for Him as they had always been for their preceeding Kings. The States General being informed by the King of all his Steps for the execution of the Treaty, know that his Majesty did openly solicite the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the same, and that he never attempted the Loyalty of the Subjects of the late Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King, by any secret methods. He had not any Intelligence, neither in the Kingdoms of <hi>Sicily</hi> or <hi>Naples,</hi> nor in any of the Dominions comprehended in the Share of the Dauphin. The favourable Opportunity was the only way to attack them. But War being once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38595:5"/> after having refused the Justice which the late Catholick King would have done to the Princes of <hi>France,</hi> it would have been hard to have put an end to it. A King in pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session of all the <hi>Spanish Monarchy</hi> without any Conditions, would have been reduced to great Extremities before he had parted with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of <hi>Sicily</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> the Province of <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puscoa,</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Milan,</hi> and the other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Places of which the Share of the Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin was to have been composed.</p>
            <p>It's to no purpose to enquire what the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences of that War might have been. It was unavoidable; and this Certainty is sufficient to shew that the Sage Precautions taken for maintaining an inviolable Peace in <hi>Europe,</hi> were perfectly overturn'd by the very <hi>Methods,</hi> that were judged only proper for entertaining it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the Inconveniencies of a War, the Uncertainties, the Misfortunes which it draws after it; had he accepted the Treaty and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Will, he must have obliged the Archduke to desist from his Right, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent himself with the Share stipulated for him.</p>
            <p>It was certainly in the Emperor's power to have done so, but will his former Refusals, push'd on to the extremity, suffer any Man to believe, that <hi>that</hi> was his Resolution, even
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38595:5"/> though he had pretended to it? Would the publick Peace have been any further ascertain'd by it? The Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> he was no ways en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in any Treaty, and he is called to the Succession by this Will, failing the Princes of <hi>France</hi> and the Archduke: What Offer consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable enough could there have been made to him, to prevent his attempting to have his new Rights made valid or to ballance the Advantages that he might reasonably hope for from them.</p>
            <p>It must not be said, that the Confederate Powers would have substituted him to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke; that's not the Case, since 'tis supposed that the Emperor would have accepted the Treaty, which the Exchange proposed to him, and which is infinitely below <hi>what Futurity offer'd him;</hi> and would not his <hi>particular Interest</hi> have oblig'd him to make the Will valid in favour of that <hi>Prince,</hi> who should thus conform himself to it?</p>
            <p>In fine, the Disposition made by his Catholic Majesty did still produce new Troubles in the Choice of a <hi>Prince</hi> to substitute in the Room of the Archduke.</p>
            <p>Since the States General insist upon that secret Article of the Treaty, they must have probably considered what <hi>Prince</hi> was in a Condition to subject the Spaniards to his Obedience, and would have been willing against the mind of the Nation, to ascend the Throne of <hi>Spain</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38595:6"/> maintain the Remainders of the dismembred Monarchy against the Enterprises of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke, authorised by the Will of the late <hi>King,</hi> and against those of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> concern'd to maintain that last Will. It does no ways appear that so many Differences could have been easily accommodated, without giving the least Trouble to the <hi>General Peace.</hi> On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, there's nothing to be foreseen but an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal War. Therefore there's a Necessity, in order to preserve the <hi>Peace,</hi> to make use of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods</hi> different from those that were proposed, at signing the Treaty of Partition.</p>
            <p>The most natural, that which is most agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for maintaining the <hi>General Peace,</hi> and the only <hi>just Method,</hi> consists in the Resolution ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the <hi>King</hi> to accept the Will of the late <hi>Catholick King.</hi> If any <hi>Prince</hi> have a Right to oppose the Dispositions of that Will, there needs no more but to read them, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd that this Right belongs only to the Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin. But since he is willing to desist from his Pretensions in favour of his Son, the Will is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted without Trouble, without effusion of Blood, and the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> receive with <hi>Peace</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi> whom his Birth, the Will of the late King, and the unanimous <hi>Desire</hi> of all the <hi>Dominions</hi> belonging to the <hi>Monarchy</hi> call to the Crown.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38595:6"/>
            <p>If any <hi>Potentate</hi> should undertake to attack so many Rights, they would justly be branded with the odious Name of <hi>Disturber of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Repose,</hi> and begin an unjust War, without any appearance of Success. Then if this War should appear Unjust when undertaken by <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates,</hi> who think it their Interest to traverse the Advantages of a <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> would it be consistent with the <hi>King's Equity,</hi> and with his <hi>tender Affection</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> to turn his Arms against a Nation, for no other Reason but because they offered their <hi>new King</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty's Grand-Son, the Crown of one of the most <hi>Potent Monarchies</hi> of <hi>Europe,</hi> and begg'd of him as the greatest of Favours to accept it. The high Dignity of <hi>Kings</hi> does not excuse them from considering whether the Wars they undertake be just. Then what Reasons could his Majesty (who is known to be a <hi>just Prince</hi>) offer for resuming Arms, to divide a Monarchy which is settled intirely upon the lawful Heir.</p>
            <p>There was a design to deprive him of his Rights. The Emperor looking upon himself to be assured of the Intentions of the late King of <hi>Spain,</hi> flattered himself with hopes of enjoying the whole Succession. Justice, Honour, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of the Crown and paternal Affection, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually obliged the King to maintain with his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38595:7"/> power the Rights of the Dauphin. His former Success was sufficient to shew what was to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Efforts of his Arms. The <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the States General were equally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to prevent the War. The <hi>King</hi> consen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to it. The <hi>Dauphin</hi> was very willing to abandon the greatest part of his Rights, on Condition of having the <hi>Dominions</hi> alloted to his share ascertain'd to him. The equal desire on all hands to maintain the <hi>Peace,</hi> produc'd the Treaty; and thus it was, that by sage <hi>Precautions</hi> taken during the Life of a <hi>Prince,</hi> whose fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and dangerous <hi>Distempers,</hi> foretold an approaching <hi>Death;</hi> It was believed, that Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice was done in part to the true Heirs, and that at the same time a solid Foundation was laid for a <hi>Peace</hi> in Europe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Disputes</hi> raised, as to the Validity of the Renunciation of the late Queen, served for a Motive to this Accommodation. In Effect, it had been of no use, if the Nullity of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation had been acknowledged as fully, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the late <hi>Catholick King</hi>'s Life, as it is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his Will.</p>
            <p>In short, it was necessary, that the <hi>King</hi> should explain himself positively, whether he would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Will, such as it is, in favour of his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or whether he absolutely rejected it. There
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38595:7"/> was no <hi>Medium,</hi> no Expedient or Change to be proposed. His Majesty accepting the Will, the Rights of the whole Succession pass uncontrovertibly to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> he is not at liberty to separate them, to accept one Part of the Succession and reject the other.</p>
            <p>The rejecting of the Will, transported all the Rights to the Archduke; nor could the true Heirs in that Case have had lawful Reason to complain of any Injustice done them. By Consequence, be it how it will, had his Majesty been minded to maintain the Conditions of the Treaty, he must have been oblig'd to attack a living Prince, Possessor of the Crown of <hi>Spain;</hi> and it's certain that the Measures he had taken with the Allies, related only to the Division of the Succession of a Prince whose death appear'd to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry near.</p>
            <p>Since the War must have been unavoidable, and that it would have been unjust if the King had fix'd his Reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to keep precisely to the Terms of the Treaty of Partition: The States General have no Reason to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that his Majesty hath prevented it by accepting the Will, except that Resolution occasion them some Prejudice; but hitherto there's none to be perceived. The only View they had in entring into that Treaty, and their sole End was to ascertain the General Peace. We owe them the Justice to declare, That they stipulated no particular Advantage to themselves, no Province, no Place, no Sea-Port depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Monarchy of <hi>Spain,</hi> either in the Old or New World, no Article for facilitating their Commerce. <hi>They,</hi> properly speaking, acted the Part of disinterested Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors betwixt the King and the Emperor, they were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to pacifie the Troubles, which the Reciprocal Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences about the Succession seem'd likely to produce in a little time: If the Emperor had been influenc'd with the same desire of maintaining the <hi>Peace,</hi> &amp; had sign'd the <hi>Treaty,</hi> the Engagements then entred into betwixt the Parties only Interested in the Succession, would have been different, but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38595:8"/> there was no Treaty except with the Mediators: And the States being inform'd of all the King's Steps with relation to the Treaty, know how useless all the Instances made at <hi>Vienna</hi> in his Name were. They know also that the Emperor being persuaded that the Arch-Duke would be called to the whole Succession of the Kingdoms of <hi>Spain,</hi> would not engage in the Partition of the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Monarchy, but in so far as it might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to extend his Authority in <hi>Italy.</hi> Let them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain then of the Emperor and his continued Refusals, if they be troubled at his Majesty's accepting the Will, which tho' he has ground to believe from the Memorial they have put into the Hands of his Ambassador, yet he is willing to suspend his Judgment, until such time as they make more serious Reflections upon this great Event. He knows the Wisdom of the Republicks Councils. All things being well examined, the States General will perhaps find, that so many considerable Dominions being added to <hi>France,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Disposition of the Treaty, might have given just Jealousie of her Power, and if it depended upon them to make Choice, the Reasons appear strong that they should prefer, to the Execution of the Treaty, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Terms, the present State of the Monarchy of <hi>Spain</hi> govern'd by a Prince of <hi>France,</hi> without the dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of its Dominions. The People of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> were already prejudiced, and endeavouring to prevent the Decisions of the Government on this Occasion: Their Complaints of the uniting the Kingdoms of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> did openly discover their Fears concerning the Trade of the <hi>Mediteranean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' the King of <hi>Spain</hi> be a Prince of <hi>France,</hi> his high Birth, his Education and Pattern, instruct him what he owes to the Welfare of his Subjects and the Interest of his Crown. Those Considerations will always have the chief Place in his Mind, they will incline him to augment the splendor of his Monarchy, and farther, the tender Affection
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38595:8"/> of the King to his Catholic Majesty, would certainly be the strongest Barrier and the most solid Assurance that <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> could desire. If his Majesty's Intention to maintain the Peace would allow the least Jealousie of his Designs, there was much more Reason to take Umbrage at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uniting of too many Dominions under one and the same Prince, if the Treaty could have been executed.</p>
            <p>Those Reflections will probably convince the States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, that Justice, the Benefits of Peace, and the very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of the Treaty would not allow the King to take other Resolutions, than that of accepting the Will of the late King of <hi>Spain;</hi> that it suits the particular Interests of the Republick of <hi>Holland,</hi> and that it is agreeable to those of all <hi>Europe;</hi> the Misfortunes then would be General, were it possible that his Majesty, after this Declaration, could have any regard to the Instances contained in their last Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial, and, in Truth, he is perswaded, that they never had any design to obtain the Effect of it. They are too clear-sighted to have formed Vows so contrary to their Light, and to the true Interests of their Republick, yet if they were capable of forgetting them so far, as to wish effectually, that his <hi>Majesty</hi> would execute the Conditions of the Treaty, they would have shewed the certain <hi>Means</hi> of effecting the Partition without a War, to the general Satisfaction of all <hi>Europe.</hi> They should at least have nam'd the Princes that were ready to join in it, the Troops for being Guarantees of the Articles of it: They should have mention'd those that the Republick of <hi>Holland</hi> was to furnish by Sea or Land. <hi>But their Memorial contained no such thing.</hi> My Lords the States propose only to grant the Emperor the Term of two <hi>Months,</hi> according to the secret Article of the Treaty: <hi>Have they already forgot, that he hath had seven Months time to deliberate in? That his Answers to the different Instances made to him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained an absolute Refusal to sign the Partition?</hi> Let them examine, <hi>What would be the Fruit of that new Proposal?</hi> The Emperor refused the Partition upon the single hopes, <hi>that the King of</hi> Spain <hi>would call the Archduke to the Succession.</hi> This Hope was vain, and the Effects have verified it to be so. In the mean time, if that was capable of suspending the Emperors Resolutions, what would not the Certainty do, which he has at present to procure the whole Succession of <hi>Spain</hi> to the Archduke: For, in short, the Delay of two Months, proposed on this Occasion by the States, would with Reason, have been looked upon by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> as the King's rejecting the VVill of his Catholick Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty. There was no Reason to demand of them to wait for an Answer so long, and besides this Answer, according to the Terms of the Treaty, could be no other than a Refusal. Thus the Regency of <hi>Spain</hi> should have been obliged in Conformity to the Intentions of the late Catholick King to devolve the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38595:9"/> Crown upon the Archduke, and the Emperor should obtain by this Delay <hi>(which my Lords the States propose)</hi> what he hath sought after with so much La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: And thus under the specious Pretext of executing the Treaty, they would ascertain for ever the Grandeur and Power of the House of <hi>Austria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>His Majesty is willing to believe that this was not their Design, they know to well that its their Interest to merit by their good Conduct the Honour of his Affection; and the continuation of his good Will. He assures himself, that they will reflect more than they have done upon the Testimonies which he gives of his Application to the maintenance of the <hi>Publick Peace;</hi> and upon the Sacrifice which he is willing to make on that Account of considerable Dominions that were to be united to his Crown, That they will change their Complaints into Thanks, and congratulate the King of <hi>Spain</hi> as soon as possible upon his accession to the Crown, and that they will endeavour to merit of the King the Good-Will and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they and their Ancestors have receiv'd of his Majesty and his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Dearest, Great Friends, Allies and Confederates, the Peace of <hi>Europe</hi> is so firmly establish'd, by the just disposal which the late King of <hi>Spain,</hi> our dearest and well-beloved Brother, hath made of his Kingdoms and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, in favour of our dearest and well-beloved Grand-Son <hi>Philip</hi> V. now K. of <hi>Spain,</hi> that we doubt not of your being glad at his Accession to the Throne. We have already made known unto him the true Affection which we bear you: <q>And since we are perswaded that his Sentiments will be agreeable to ours, the strict Correspondence which shall henceforward be maintain'd betwixt our Crown and that of <hi>Spain,</hi> will give us new Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, of shewing you how much we Interest our selves in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you, and the sincere Friendship that we entertain for you; the Count <hi>de Briord,</hi> our Ambassador Extraordinary, will give you new Assurances of it; and, in the mean time, we pray God, that he may take you into his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Protection.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Wrote at <hi>Versailles,</hi>
                  <date>Nov. 29. 1700.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sign'd, <hi>LOUIS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I The Subscriber, Ambassador Extraordinary of <hi>France,</hi> having receiv'd Orders from my Master, to give your Lordship's the Letter that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty hath wrote to you, to notifie the Accession of King <hi>Philip</hi> V. his Grand-Son to the Monarchy of <hi>Spain,</hi> and to communicate to you at the same time the just Motives that oblig'd him to accept the Will of the late King of <hi>Spain,</hi> which are contain'd in the Memorial join'd to the King's Letter. The said Ambassador hath caused the Letter and Memorial to be deliver'd to M. <hi>de Haren,</hi> President for this Week. <q>I wish your Lordships may make all the Reflections upon it suitable to the present state of Affairs, and to the Good and Advantage of this Republick, which may and ought to rely upon the ASSURANCES, which he hath Order from the King his Master to give your Lordships, of the Continuation of his Friendship, and of his Majesty's sincere Desire to maintain the Alliance and good Corres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence which he hath with this State. The said Ambassador is perswaded, That your Lordships will correspond with the favourable Intentions of the King his Master.</q>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>At the <hi>Hague,</hi>
                     <date>Decemb. 4. 1700.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Sign'd, <hi>BRIORD.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <pb facs="tcp:38595:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>